A Guide to the Graham, Tate and related families Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #9232-n
Graham, Tate and related families Papers 1798-1979 bulk (1857-1865)
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
9232-n
ca. 135 items
Agnes Graham Sanders Riley and Andrew Trigg Sanders Sr.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated to the Library on March 18, 1987 by Agnes Graham Sanders Riley of Lexington, Kentucky and Andrew Trigg Sanders, Sr. of Richmond, Virginia, in memory of their parents, Elizabeth Graham and Edwin Hanson Sanders.
Scope and Content
This material, 1798 (1857-1865) 1979, which includes ca. 135 items, concerns the Graham and Tate families of Wythe County, Virginia, and includes correspondence, financial and legal papers, genealogical and historical information, and an ambrotype of Squire David Graham.
The family papers consist chiefly of letters, 1857-1865, from Charles Beverly Tate(Feb. 18, 1847-July 10, 1925), James Graham Tate(Dec. 14, 1840-Aug. 25, 1864), and William Hanson Tate(Sep. 19, 1837-May 15, 1864) to their father, Charles Campbell Tate(Jan. 30, 1808-May 27, 1874), and siblings, Nannie Montgomery Tate(Feb. 8, 1843-Jan. 30, 1923) and John Montgomery Tate(July 15, 1833-Nov. 7, 1881).
Charles Beverly Tate entered Virginia Military Institute in 1862 at the age of fifteen. During the Battle of New Market, where his brother William was fatally wounded, he was a cadet private in Company C and was detailed to serve in the artillery section of the V.M.I. Corps. He continued in service with the corps until the evacuation of Richmond in April 1865. On January 22, 1865, a few days after being appointed a sergeant in Company B, Charles wrote his father, asking his advice as to whether or not he should resign V.M.I. to join the army, and, if so, what branch he should enter.
James Graham Tate entered Emory and Henry College in 1859 and remained until the spring of 186l. His letters during this time were mostly concerned with school, family and friends in Wythe County, and wanting news of the "ladies." On January 10, 1861, he wrote his brother John mentioning that he wanted to finish school but that he anticipated being called upon to fight soon. On May ll, 1861, he enlisted in the Wythe Grays which later became Company A of the 4th Regiment of Virginia, organized April 28, 1861; the regiment was accepted into Confederate service on July 1, 1861. In June 1861 he wrote from Harper's Ferry, Virginia about elections in his company and adapting to life in the barracks; and later, from Camp Stevens, Berkeley County, he described the burning of the Potomac Bridge and public buildings which had been ordered by Joseph E. Johnston as the Confederates evacuated Harper's Ferry. The 4th Regiment became a part of the Virginia First Brigade, which had established itself as the "Stonewall Brigade" at the First Bull Run Campaign, July 1, 1861. During August and September of that year, he discusses the loss of his knapsack and blankets after a skirmish, requested that his father send "Burkhart" to help in the mess and take care of luggage, and mentioned the court martial of a deserter, Francis Tomney. And, as their marching continued, he wondered about their purpose. An interesting letter of April 3, 1862, pertains to their orders to take their pieces of artillery to Staunton, Virginia and having to use muskets again, the men wanting transfers to artillery and cavalry companies, and losing some 76 men in their regiment while fighting on March 23 (probably at the First Battle of Kernstown, Virginia). It was not until April 30 that "Stonewall" Jackson left Elk Run heading for Staunton, which became a major part of the Shenandoah Valley Campaign. During 1863, the Confederate armies seemed to be faced with severe hardships, including a shortage of rations, the reduction of transportation, and the scarcity of "white labor." In the spring of 1863, James revealed his disappointment in southern farmers for avoiding their duty by not growing grain to feed the men in the Confederate armies. In a March 1863 letter, Tate mentions "Jeb" Stuart's fight with the enemy, calling it a "right brilliant little affair," probably in reference to the Battle of Kelly's Ford in late December when the Federal Army pulled back from the site after a day's fighting. The following month, April 1863, he writes of marching toward Port Royal to meet the enemy who was crossing [the Rappahannock], only to find that they had recrossed. At this time there had been a three-day Federal expedition operating from Bell Plain to Port Royal. In late October 1863, Tate describes the engagement at Bristoe Station on the 14th which brought criticism to General Ambrose P. Hill who had "ordered only two brigades" to make the charge on General George Gordon Meade's Army of the Potomac. The following year, James Graham Tate was killed at Shepherdstown, Virginia on August 25.
William Hanson Tate became a cadet at the Virginia Military Institute on July 30, 1857, and was a member of the Cadet Corps. While at V.M.I., he wrote of living arrangements, social activities, new cadet initiation, and news of family and friends. In his September 4, 1857, letter, he gave a lengthy description of living in "encampment," mentioning the barracks and guard duty. As early as October 1857, he was looking forward to the cadets' trip to Richmond in February 1858; and, on March 8, 1858, he wrote an interesting and lengthy account of the trip to Richmond during which the cadets represented the Virginia Military Institute at the dedication of the Crawford equestrian statue of George Washington in the city's Capitol Square on February 22, 1858. In the fall of 1859 he became a teacher at the Anchor and Hope Academy as all V.M.I. men were expected to serve some time as teachers. Between October 1859 and June 1860, his letters contained news of the school; and, on February 14, 1860, he mentioned a trip to Richmond being planned by "Uncle David" [Squire David Graham] and his father. During this time he was on the muster roll of the Wythe Grays, although his real military service was in the 51st Regiment of the Virginia Volunteers. He was elected First Lieutenant upon its organization in May 1861. On November 20, 1861, he described their retreat from Cotton Hill which resulted in considerable loss of property, General John Buchanan Floyd's delay and retreat tactics, and illness among the men. In May and June 1862, his letters pertained to skirmishes in Princeton, and mentioned Colonel Gabriel Calvin Wharton, General Henry Heth, General [John Buchanan] Floyd, and General Humphrey Marshall. Later, on August 26, 1863, he wrote of a visit to the "Stone Wall Brigade" while at Liberty Mills. In November 1863, in camp near Blountville, Tennessee, he wrote of his command witnessing the execution of three deserters from the Confederate Army, their orders to move toward Knoxville, Tennessee and rumors of Knoxville being captured by General James Longstreet. During November 4-22 the siege of Knoxville was underway, but the Confederate Army was forced to retreat in early December. On May 1, 1864, while encamped near his home, Max Meadows, he wrote that it was his duty to remain with his company while so close to their home. Soon afterwards, on May 15th, he was killed in the Battle of New Market while leading a charge. At his death he was Captain of Company B, 51st Regiment, Wharton's Brigade.
Organization
The material was received at the Library in packets or folders with identifying notes by the donor, which was taken into consideration when the material was arranged. The collection is divided into three series: I. Correspondence; II. Miscellaneous; and, III. Genealogical.
Container List
- I. Correspondence
  - Charles Beverly Tate to Charles Campbell Tate and Nannie Montgomery Tate, w/ transcripts, 1863-1865 (Box Box 1)
  - James Graham Tate to Nannie Montgomery Tate, w/ transcripts, 1859-1860 (Box Box 1)
  - James Graham Tate to Charles Campbell Tate, John Montgomery Tate, and Nannie Montgomery Tate, w/ transcripts, 1861 (Box Box 1)
  - James Graham Tate to Charles Campbell Tate and Nannie Montgomery Tate, w/ transcripts, 1862 (Box Box 1)
  - James Graham Tate to Charles Campbell Tate, w/ transcripts, 1863 (Box Box 1)
  - James Graham Tate to Nannie Montgomery Tate, and a letter about the death of James Graham Tate, w/ transcripts, 1862, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - James Graham Tate miscellaneous, 1861-1864, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - William Hanson Tate to Nannie Montgomery Tate, w/ transcripts, 1857-1860; (3 folders) (Box Box 1)
  - William Hanson Tate to Nannie Montgomery Tate and a cousin, w/ transcripts, 1861-1862 (Box Box 1)
  - William Hanson Tate to Charles Campbell Tate and Nannie Montgomery Tate, w/ transcripts, 1863 (Box Box 1)
  - William Hanson Tate to Charles Campbell Tate and Nannie Montgomery Tate, and a telegram about the death of William Hanson Tate, w/ transcripts, 1864, n.d. (Box Box 1)
- II. Miscellaneous
  - Financial and Legal Papers of the Graham Family, and related documents, 1798-1887, n.d. (Box Box 2)
  - Miscellanous, 1835-1904, n.d. (Box Box 2)
  - Framed Ambrotype of Squire David Graham, n.d. (Box Box 2)
- III. Genealogical
  - Genealogical Information on the Graham Family and Tate Family, 1901-1979, n.d. (Box Box 2)
  - "The Graham Family" by Nannie Montgomery Tate Graham, 1918 (Box Box 2)
  - "Letters of a V.M.I. Cadet, 1857-1858," Wythe County Historical Review, edited by Agnes Graham Sanders Riley, 1973 (Box Box 2)
  - Max Meadows, Wythe County Historic Sites, 1938, n.d. (Box Box 2)
  - "The Tate Family of Wythe County, Virginia, " Wythe County Historical Review, by Agnes Graham Sanders Riley, with exhibits of material used, 1975 (Box Box 2)